Finding Aid for the Kathryn McCarthy Papers, 1911-1955
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Kathryn McCarthy Papers, 1911-1955
Mus. Arc. 7
McCarthy, Kathryn, d. 1970
1 box
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The Kathryn McCarthy Papers contain a bound notebook of notes from music lessons and correspondence between McCarthy and Schillinger System teacher, Richard Benda.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Kathryn McCarthy was a music teacher in Buffalo, N.Y. She was a lecturer in music at the University at Buffalo Evening School, 1929-1936 and director of music theory in the First Settlement School in Buffalo. Studied piano and music literature with Evelyn Choate, elementary theory with Mary Howard, took a director's course at Cornell University, 1913, courses at New York University, 1915, instrumentation and composition at Columbia University, studied composition, instrumentation, and pedagogy with Hugo Leichtentritt in Berlin, 1914, piano with F. Mufchim in Petrograd, 1921, composition, instrumentation, and pedagogy with Jean Gallon in Paris, piano with E. Monod in Paris, and studies with A. Madley Richardson and Arthur Newstead in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The Kathryn McCarthy Papers contain ten folders of materials related to McCarthy's music lessons in composition, counterpoint, and the Schillinger System. Teachers of McCarthy included A. Madeley Richardson (1868-1949) and Richard Benda (d. 1978).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
I. Lesson Book in Composition and Counterpoint.
II. Correspondence. Correspondence to and from Schillinger method teacher, Richard Benda. Folders 2-10.
Container List
- Lesson Book, 1911-1921, I.; Folder 1
  - Lesson book labeled "Kathryn McCarthy, Counterpoint, Composition" 1911-1921, 1 bound notebook (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The contents are primarily text, with a small number of musical examples, and seem to be notes taken during classes. Pages are filled through the page stamped "p. 291". The notebook is also inscribed inside the front cover: "London, 1911, Berlin, 1914, Paris, 1921."
- Correspondence, 1950-1955, II.; Folders 2-10
  Arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Kathryn McCarthy to Richard Benda, March 9, no year, 1 manuscript leaf (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Richard Benda to Kathryn McCarthy, October 5, 1950 and October 23, 1950, 2 typescript letters (2 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Cover letters sent from Benda with an outline of lessons (not included) and an audio recording (also, not included).
  - Richard Benda letter to Kathryn McCarthy, June 8, 1955, 1 manuscript letter (2 leaves, 3 leaves of music) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Letter accompanied by musical examples.
  - Richard Benda letter to Kathryn McCarthy, June [unclear date], 1955, 1 manuscript letter (1 leaf) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Postcard from Benda requesting confirmation for receipt of material
  - Richard Benda letter to Kathryn McCarthy, September 6, 1955, 1 manuscript letter (1 leaf, 2 leaves of music) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Richard Benda letter to Kathryn McCarthy, December, 1955, 1 manuscript letter (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Christmas card
  - Advertisement for Richard Benda's course, Strata Harmony, Composition, Orchestration for Radio, Film, Television, undated, 1 printed leaf (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Advertisement for Richard Benda's course, An Important Advance in Schillinger Instruction, undated, 1 printed leaf (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Advertisement for Richard Benda's course, The Schillinger System in Accordion Instruction, undated, 1 printed leaf (Box 1, Folder 10)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Richardson, A. Madeley (Alfred Madeley), 1868-1949; Benda, Richard, d. 1978
Subjects
Musicians--Correspondence; Counterpoint; Composition (Music)
Genres
Correspondence
Associated Material
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
Lessons. A. Madeley Richardson. Treasure Room M1 R393 l.
Two volumes of composition studies based on models by Beethoven, Handel, Bach and Haydn, inscribed by Kathryn McCarthy, 1924.